它取名自罗马战神
It takes its name from the Roman God of War,
夜空一颗遥远的暗红色的星球
a distant, rusty orb in the night sky,
几百年来引起遐想的地方
a source of rampant speculations for centuries
是另一个文明的所在吗？
Could it be home to a rival civilization?
它的表面真的有张人脸吗？
Is there really a face on its surface?
这个迷人的行星邻居仍然迷惑着我们
This intriguing planetary neighbor still captivates us
即是未来殖民的潜在基地
And as both a potential base for future colonization
还保持着40亿年古老的生命秘密
And the keeper of 4 billion year old biological secrets
火星 红色的行星
Mars, the red planet
可能掌握着我们未来和过去的关键
may hold the keys to both our future and our past
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
历史频道·宇宙第一季第2集 火星·红色行星
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：射手网 调校：TIAN@CMCT 招募Q号: 76846146
如果人类曾经在我们太阳系另一个地方居住过的话
If human beings ever inhabited another world in our solar system,
这是最有可能的候选之地
this is the most likely candidate
红色行星 火星
The red planet, Mars
对一个地球来的访客 火星旅行
To a visitor from Earth, a tour of Mars
可能非常象让人想起家乡的地方
might be very reminiscent of places back home
象南加利福尼亚莫哈韦沙漠
Places like Southern California's Mojavi Desert
地理和天文生物学家肯恩·尼尔森
Geo- and astro-biologist Ken Nealson,
发现这个沙漠如此象火星
find this desert area, so much like Mars,
他来到这里试图更好地了解火星上的条件
he comes here to try to better understand conditions on the red planet
在着死亡之地周游 你会看到
You travel around here in the doom baggy and you'll see
火星上的死亡之地一样的面貌
features that look just like the doom features on Mars
如果你更深入的环顾周围 看到所有的这些红色的山丘
If you go further and look in the background, and see all of this red hills,
满是氧化铁 就象在火星上看到的一样
full of iron oxydes that we see on Mars
火星堆满了铁
Mars is filled with iron,
和氧化铁 基本上生了锈 化为了尘埃
and its oxidized iron, basically rust, turns into dust particles
除了美丽的山丘外 还有红色的大气层
and in addition to the beautiful dunes, you have this red atmosphere
有时行星的表面充满了红色
sometime red all over the surface of the planet
巨大的尘埃风暴
Huge dust storms
不是随随便便叫它为红色行星的
They don't call it the red planet for nothing
然而火星的地形与地球相仿
But while much of the martian terrain is similair to Earth,
一些地理面貌完全就象
some geological features dwarf,
我们的地球上的某些特征
any of there kind on our home planet,
一座山命名为Olympus Mons 拉丁文的奥林匹斯山
a mountain named the Olympus Mons, latin for mount Olimpus,
是太阳系里所知的最高的山峰
is the tallest known peak in the solar system
是座著名的死火山 高耸在火星表面15英里
It's a know dormed volcano, that rises fifteen miles above the martian surface
假如你把奥林匹斯山的照片
If you took a picture of Olympus mons,
和珠穆朗玛峰放在一起 和
an put it next to mount Everest, and
和夏威夷最大的岛 甚至把岛的海下部分一起拿上来
and the big island of Hawaii, even taken all the way down to the base of the ocean,
比较火星上的奥林匹斯山 简直就是小不点了
they look like molehills, compared with Olympus Mons on Mars
那座山如此之大 你在它的斜坡上时
That mount is so large you can be on its slopes
不会感觉是在火山的斜坡上
and you would not know that you're on a slope of a volcano
在你登上山顶之前 这是因为它的基座实在是大
because the based is so huge, before you get to its sommit
然而 受启发的是火星表面看来
Yet, as inspiring as the martian surface appears,
对人类生存是个残酷荒凉之地
it is a brutal, inhospitable zone for human beings
绿色航行…
Green board...
五… 四… 三… 二… 一…
5... 4... 3... 2... 1...
点火 delta2号升空
Engine start and lift off of the delta 2 rocket
携带着精神号从地球飞向火星
carrying the Spirit from Earth to planet Mars
它是冰凉的 干燥的 荒凉的
It's cold, it's dry, it's desolated,
有尘埃风暴 一次可以遮盖天空几个星期 甚至几个月
there are dust storms, that can darken the skies for weeks, even months at a time
在晚上温度下降到零下100度
It goes down to a hundred degrees below zero
在每一个夜晚
at night, every night
配合这个寒冷的环境是没有氧气的大气层
Compounding this cool conditions, is an atmosphere with no oxygen
火星的空气和偶尔的云层
Martian air and even occasional clouds formations
几乎充满了二氧化碳
are made up almost entirely of carbon dioxide
所以他不是个好地方 如果你正好在那里 不会喜欢它的
So it's not a nice place, you wouldn't enjoy it, if you're right there
火星是地球的小的近亲
Mars is small, relative to the Earth
只有地球的一半大
Only about half the size of our planet
距离地球从没少于过3400万英里
Its distance from us it's never less than 34 million miles
它看起来只是天空上一颗小小的红色星球
It appears as nothing more than a tiny red orb in our night sky
尽管如此 几百年来 火星还是迷惑了人们
Even so, Mars has captivated human kind for centuries
它的名字取自罗马战神的名字
The planet takes its name from the Roman God of war
罗马人将战争和动荡和这个遥远的地方联系在一起
The Romans associated this distant world with ostility and unrest,
是因为它那血一般的颜色 而且还因为它在天上与众不同的运动
because of its blood-like colour, and because of its distinctive movement in the sky
火星奇迹 它不会做其他星球做的事情
Mars wonders It doesn't do what the stars do
红色星球有时会在天上向后移动
The red planet occasionally appears to be moving backward across the sky
其举止迷惑了观察者几百年
A behavior that confounded observers for centuries
然而在1514年 深入研究了这颗行星的运动后
But in 1514, close study of this planetary movement,
顶尖的波兰天文学家哥白尼
lead Polish astronomer Nicholas Copernicus
革命性地定义了太阳系
to a revolutionary understanding of the solar system
在许多有记录的历史上 人们认为地球是宇宙的中心
For much of recording history, people thought that Earth was at the center of the Universe,
接着来了哥白尼 他说道
Along come Copernicus, and he says?
不 地球不可能是宇宙的中心
No, maybe the Earth isn't at the center of the Universe
物体围绕着太阳运行也许可以解释这一切
Maybe the explanation for all this is that, things are going around the Sun
如果行星围绕着太阳运行 那么我们能够解释为什么
And if all the planets are going around the Sun, then we can explain why
当地球越过在轨的火星时
as Earth passes Mars in the orbit,
火星会往后倒退的原因
Mars begins to wonder in our sky
看上去往这边跑 接着就往那边跑
Looks like it's going this way and then the source goes this way
哥白尼通过一段时间的观察
By the time of Copernicus'observations,
火星和地球相互在各自的轨道上运行
Mars and the Earth had been passing each other and their respective orbit,
有45亿年了
for some 4 5 billion years
足够的时间让两颗行星发展成为两个非常不同的世界
Time enough for the two planets to evolved into very different worlds
一个温暖 潮湿 富含氧气
One warm, wet and oxygen rich
另一个则寒冷 干燥 没有氧气
The other cold, dry and oxygen depleted
但是现在相信 它们的差异并不完全如此
Yet it's now believed that the differences weren't always so stark
科学家现在认为火星曾经也很温暖
Scientists today think that Mars was once warm enough
大量的水在其表面流淌
for large amounts of liquid water to flow across its surface
当我们观察现在的火星时 卫星的最佳图象
When we look at Mars today, in our best satellite images,
告诉了我们和第一次火星探测飞行看到的相同的信息
they tell us the same message we heard from the first mission to Mars,
今天的火星上没有液态水
and that there is no liquid water on the planet today
但无可争辩的事实是
but there's virtually incontrovertible evidence
火星上曾经有过水
that there was water there in the past
大家都知道 水流过任何一种土壤时
Everybody knows that when water flows to any sort of dirt,
会有其特征的
there are caratteristic structures,
水流淌过还有其他的作用
there are other functions of that water running through,
而当看到卫星传回的火星的图象时
and when we look at the pictures of Mars, of satellites images,
我们看到非常类似的构造
we see very similar structures
引导我们作出肯定的结论
leading us to the absolute conclusion
火星曾经比现在温暖和湿润得多得多
that Mars was once far warmer and wetter than it is now
今天的火星当然是片荒漠之地
Mars of course is a harsh desert today,
那么曾经发生了什么？
so what could have happened?
什么宇宙过程会给太阳第四颗行星
What cosmic process could have brought about such a dramatic transformation
带来如此戏剧性的变化呢？
of the fourth planet from the Sun
故事还得从太阳系说起
The story begins with the origin of the solar system
45亿年前的某个地方
Somewhere in the range of 4 5 billions years ago,
我们的太阳系从一个超新星里诞生了
our solar system sprang from a supernova
一个恒星的爆发喷发出
A stellar explosion emitting a swirling mass
粒子和气体的旋涡状物质
of molecular particles and gasses
这个旋涡状物质或"星云"开始冷却
This swirling mass or "nebula" began to cool
而且 随着冷却开始聚集 并分开变成粒子环
and, as it did, it condensed and separated into rings of particles
这些粒子开始吸附或
These particles began to accrete or gradually
逐渐结合形成行星
come together to form planets
增长的过程产生了热
The accretion process creates heat
较重的粒子下沉到物质团的中心
and heavier particles sink to the center of the accumulating mass
所以火星最终形成了一个熔化的铁核
So Mars eventually formed a molten iron core
这个熔核产生了一个强大的磁场
This churning molten core generated a powerful magnetic field
磁场环绕着火星 就象保护盾一样
The field projected outwards surrounding Mars like a protective shield,
阻挡了来自太阳的有害射线
blocking harmful emissions from the Sun
来自太阳持续的压力我们称为太阳风
You have this constant pressure from the Sun which we call the solar wind
太阳由质量子 电子 宇宙射线组成
The solar wind is made of protons, electrons, cosmic rays,
所有的带电粒子
all of these kinds of charged particles
会电离大气层
that could ionize the atmosphere,
就象我们说的 把大气吹走
as we call, sputter it away
但是火星最终失去了它的保护盾
But eventually Mars lost its protective shield
和大部分的大气层
and most of its atmosphere
这个过程结束的时候 火星开始冷却
The moment the accretion process ended the planet began to cool
铁核不能再产生磁场
The iron core was no longer able to generate this magnetic field
接着太阳风开始重击火星表面
and then the solar wind started pounding the surface of Mars
这是大多数人相信的假设
That's a scenario that a lot of people believe
大气层的丧失剥夺了火星的温暖和压力
The loss of atmosphere stripped the martian surface of warmth and pressure
因为水需要温度和压力才能保持液态
and since water needs both warmth and pressure to remain in liquid form,
在火星表面水无法保持稳定
water is no longer stable on the martian surface
如果把一盘水放在火星上
If we put a pan of water out there on Mars it's gonna
会很快蒸发 同时也会结冰
evaporate very fast and try to freeze at the same time
不管是蒸发还是结冰 你都不会有液态的水了
One or the other will win out, but you won't have a nice liquid pan of water
不是说火星上一点没有水
That's not to say however that there's no water on the planet at all
虽然火星上不存在液态的水
While liquid water is no longer stable on Mars,
但冰冻的水 冰 就是另一个故事了
frozen water, ice, is a different story
有证据证明直到今天
And evidence suggests that still today
大量的水结的冰可能就在火星极地下面
tons of water ice might lie just below the martian polar caps
锁定在那里的冰可能就是
Locked within that ice might just be
太空探险的圣杯
the Holy Grail of space exploration
可以通过地球上望远镜看到它的存在
They're visible through simple telescopes on Earth
在经过太空接近火星时
and they are inquestionably the first planetary features noticeable
这被清楚地表明为它的第一特征
during an approach to Mars through space,
在火星的极地
the martian polar caps
神秘的白色冰雪世界
Mysterious snowy white ice worlds,
覆盖在红色星球的顶部和底部
sheathing the top and bottom of the red planet
事实上我们叫做干冰的是二氧化碳
Actually what we call dry ice is frozen carbon dioxide
大气层非常干燥 几乎都是二氧化碳
the atmosphere is very thin and it's nearly all carbon dioxide,
所以在非常寒冷的情况下会结晶
so when it gets very cold what condenses out
是二氧化碳的雪 二氧化碳的冰
is carbon dioxide snow, carbon dioxide ice
虽然白色的冰帽的确是火星多彩的特征
But while the white caps are certainly a colorful planetary feature,
但不是二氧化碳自身的结晶体
it's not the frozen concentrations of CO2 themselves
那是科学家最感兴趣的
that are of most interest to scientists
认为隐藏在极帽下的东西
It's what's thought to be hidden beneath the polar caps
具有重要的意义
that could have massive significance
潜伏在覆土下的
Lurking just below the top soil,
可能是数百万吨的冰冻水
may be millions of tons of frozen water
隐藏的水的冰看上去
Water ice hidden from view
从极地向四面八方放射出去数百英里
appears to radiate out hundreds of miles in all directions from the poles
让科学家认为那可能是过去海洋
and leading scientists think it could be the residue
的残留物
of once vast oceans
可能水现在冻结在地表下面的冻土层里
Likely the water's now frozen, in a kind of permafrost beneath the surface,
但是火星不同的地方可能会有压力和温度
but maybe there are pressures and temperatures in various areas of Mars
融化冰 可能会
that have liquified the ice and created perhaps
产生液体的水
aqua forms
我们可以看到撞击产生的坑 是一颗小行星撞击火星形成的
We can see craters in an impact This up an asteroid that's hit Mars
溅起大量物质
blown up a lot of stuff, it doesn't blow out
没有象在月亮上那样溅飞干燥的粉尘 产生闪光和碎石
dry powder like on the Moon and make rays and rubble,
变成泥泞的泥浆
it turns out kind of a muddy slurry of stuff
所以结论是实际上撞击到了冰
So the conclusion is that you're actually impacting into ice
就象加拿大北方的永冻层 冻土带土层
like northern Canada permafrost layers, a tundra kind of stuff
轨道太空船已经看到了很强的指标
Orbiting spacecrafts have picked up strong indicators
说明火星极地固态水的存在
for the existence of water ice at the martian poles
远距离的土壤测量已经发现高级别的氢
Remote measurements of soil composition have detected high levels of hydrogen
水当然是一份氧和两份氢组成的
Water of course is one part oxygen and two parts hydrogen,
所以冰可能覆盖在那些区域的地表之下是无可辩驳的
so the possibility of ice hiding below the surface in those areas is overwhelming
而在火星极地有冰存在的明显证据
But while strong evidence of ice at the martian poles may be relatively new
那里存在着水 会联想到一个世纪前普遍认为的
speculation that water existed there became common more than a century ago,
红色星球上也存在着智能生命
and its implication that intelligent life could also exist on the red planet,
在地球上引起广泛的盼望
elicited wide spread anxiety on Earth
特别是在20世纪前半个世纪
for much of the first half of the twentieth century
天文学家在1610年首次将望远镜指向火星
Astronomers pointed the first telescope towards Mars in 1610
随着望远镜技术的不断改进
As spyglass technology steadily improved,
红色星球模糊的印象
a blurred image of the red planet
比过去任何时候更靠近地球观察员的眼睛
drew ever closer to the eyes of earthly observers
在1877年 望远镜能够放大远方行星的映象
By 1877 telescopes could enlarge the image of the distant planet,
所以能够大致看清远方的东西
so that it appeared roughly the size of a dime held at harm's length
当然按现代标准算不得什么
Certainly not impressive by modern standards,
但对米兰天文台台长来说已经足够了
but it was enough for the director of the Milano observatory,
乔伐尼·齐亚巴雷利
Giovanni Schiaparelli,
努力勾勒火星表面 对其地貌进行命名
to attempt to sketch the martian surface and name its geological features
齐亚巴雷利窥视那朦胧多变的映象
Schiaparelli peered at the hazy shifty visage
几个月里一晚接着一晚
night after night for months
他看到了火星表面他认为的十字交叉线
And he sees what he thinks are criss-cross lines on the surface of Mars
后来证明 他看到的不完全是那里有什么
It turns out later, what he saw isn't exactly
但是通过他那粗糙的望远镜还是能看到什么的
what's up there, but still through his crude telescope that's what he could see
尊敬的意大利天文学家勾画了这些线条
Respected italian astronomers sketched these lines
并给它们取了名字
and gave them a name
齐亚巴雷利认为那些线条象
Schiaparelli interpreted these lines as
某种河床 他并不真的了解
channels of some sort, he didn't really know
在这 他用意大利语称它们是"canali"
Well, the italian word that he applied to them was "canali",
那个词 翻译成英语应该译成"河床"(channels)
that word, translated to english should have been translated as "channels",
但是相反被误译成"运河"(canals)
but instead it got mistranslated as "canals"
由于自然界没有看到过直线
Since straight lines do not normally appear in nature,
齐亚巴雷利勾画的时候产生了念头
Schiaparelli sketches gave birth to the idea
即火星上应该存在智能生命的某种形态
that some form of intelligent life must exist on Mars
这是一个引人瞩目的想法
It was an arresting notion,
天文学家一直为之广泛辩论
widely debated among the astronomers of the day
后来在1894年
Later in 1894,
一个叫帕西瓦尔 罗威尔的波士顿富人
a wealthy Bostonian named Percival Lowell
竟然被这个想法吸引
was so intrigued by this possibility
买了大望远镜安放在
that he paid to have a large telescope constructed on a mountain side
亚利桑那州旗杆市的山旁
in Flagstaff, Arizona
他化了接下来的20年对红色星球进行观察
He spent the next two decades observing, sketching
勾画和推测
and speculating about the red planet
他自信已经看到火星上直线组成的网络
He convinced himself that he was seeing networks of straight lines on Mars,
他认为那就是运河
which he thought were canals,
在那些日子里和巴拿马运河一起成为大新闻
what was the big news at the day with the Panama canal,
那是伟大的行星文明创造的 他们建造了运河
that's what great planetary civilisations do, they build canals
所以这是火星上从极地冰帽引水的运河
So this was canals to bring the water down from the polar ice caps on Mars,
由于是寒冷 远离太阳 还是干燥
which are cold and far from the Sun and dry,
所以他知道 所以他认为
so he knew that and so he thought,
好了 在火星上他们必须为了生活运水
well, they have to move the water to live on Mars
那个想法正好刺激了每个人 火星上有个文明
That idea just electrified everybody, that there was a civilisation on Mars
在此背景下 1938年万圣节的晚上
Against this backdrop on Halloween night 1938
一个名叫奥森·威尔斯的年轻播音员
A young actor named Orson Wells
推出了[世界大战]的广播剧
broadcasted a dramatisazion of War of the Worlds
一部英国作家H G 威尔斯的小说
A novella by british author H G Wells
描写险恶的火星人登陆地球 并进行肆虐
In which sinister martians land on Earth and wreak havoc
我们把你带回Grovers磨房的卡尔·菲利普斯那里
We now return you to Carl Phillips at Grovers Mill
女士们 先生们 我在这里等一会儿 发生了一些情况
ladies and gentlemen, here I am wait a minute, something's happening
有一架飞机从那镜子弹出 跳在那路人的右边
There's a plane springing from that mirror and it leaps right at the advancing men
好家伙 他们变成了火焰!
Good Lord, they're turning into flame!
成千上万的市民认为这是真的入侵
Thousands of citizens believed the invasion was real
我对此深深地感到震惊和哀悼
I'm deeply shocked and deeply regret for,
误会是短暂的
The misunderstanding was short lived
然而即便如此 广播只是给大众关于火星上
But even so the broadcast only served to fuel public speculation
可能存在智能生命的猜想添油加醋
about potential intelligent life on Mars
火星:吸引着人类数千年
Mars: it has intrigued human kind for thousands of years
20世纪中期
And in mid 20th century
人类终于近距离地观察神秘的行星
humans finally got a closer look at the mysterious planet
1964年 美国航空航天局 NASA
In 1964 the National Aeronautic and Space Admininstration, NASA,
向红色星球发射了小探险飞船
launched the small exploration spacecraft toward the red planet
它的名字叫做水手4号 带有一个电视摄像机
Its name was Mariner 4, it had a television camera
它的使命是飞过火星 传回图象
and its mission was to fly past Mars and send back pictures
它只能经过一次
It could only make one pass
科学家伴随着激动
Scientists were filled with anxious excitement
充满了期待
at the prospect of what they might see
将会看到城市？将会看到运河？将会看到森林？
Well it is gonna see cities, is it gonna see canals, is it gonna see forests?
然而所有能看到的都是弹坑
But all of what it saw it was craters
飞船发回的图象只是非常模糊 弹坑看上去就象月亮上的一样
It sent back pictures which just were very fuzzy and showed craters like on the moon
这是一个巨大的失望
It was a huge let down
水手4号的图象显示了一个干燥多坑的沙漠的情景
The Mariner 4 images revealed a dry cratered desert like
表面死寂的行星
and seemingly dead planet
有点象月亮 一点空气吹着周围的沙尘
Sort of like the moon with a little air to blow the dust around
但是探索火星的热情只是被降温
But the enthusiasm for exploring Mars was only tempered
6年后 在1971年
And 6 years later, in 1971,
NASA向红色星球发射了另一艘飞船:水手9号
NASA sent another spacecraft to the red planet: Mariner 9
但是这时 舍弃了仅仅经过火星
But this time, rather than just making a single pass by Mars
水手9号被制造成围绕火星几个星期
Mariner 9 was engineered to orbit the planet for weeks
做一个完整的扫描
and do a complete mapping
努力得到了回报
The effort paid off
在等待了一个火星大范围的沙尘暴后
After waiting out a planet wide dust storm,
水手9号开始发回壮观的图象
Mariner 9 started returning spectacular images
它发现了塔尔西斯高地
It discovered the Tharsis bulge,
火星大肚皮的地方 靠近赤道
The source of potbelly of the planet, near the equator
它的隆起是由于集中了大规模的火山
The bulge is a result of concentrated and massive volcanic activity
塔尔西斯高地显示出来的特写
The dominant feature of the Tharsis bulge
是最高的火山:奥林匹斯山
is the monster volcano: Olympus mons
奥林匹斯山的大小相当于密苏里州 如果把它放到美国中部
Olympus mons is about the size of Missouri If you put it in the middle of the US,
它将占据那张地图
it would dominate that picture
如果它重大爆发 火山的大小
If it had a major eruption, a volcano of that size
或许会吞没密苏里州的每一个地方
would probably full up one state on every side of Missouri
所以 嗯 我的家乡在衣阿华州 将会被熔岩覆盖
so, uh, my home town in Iowa would be under lava
有趣的是 我们认为它是由三座火山组成的
Interestingly it's composed of we think three separate volcanos
或至少以三种不同的方式喷发 如果你…
or at least it's erupted in three different ways, if you...
在它顶上飞过 你会看到三个分开的火山口
fly over the top you see three separate calderas
所以不仅仅是三倍大 而且还是地质上的怪物
So it isn't just three times larger, this is a monster geological event
事实上你站在它的边缘 它的斜坡是如此的平缓
When infact if you're on the edge, the slope is so gradual
山顶在100英里以外
and the peak is more than a hundred miles away
你不会知道那就是火山 它是巨大的
and that you wouldn't know that it was a volcano And it's that massive
奥林匹斯山并不孤单
And Olympus mons is not alone
数百英里的东南向的山脉
A few hundreds miles South-East of the mountains
三个其它的火山斜排成一列与庞大的火山保持着等距离
stands a diagonal row of three other, evenly spaced enormous volcanos
每一个都比地球上的同类大
Each larger than any of its type on Earth
然而 作为宏伟的
Yet as magnificent as it is,
塔尔西斯地区并不是水手9号
The Tharsis region isn't the only spectacular
发现的唯一壮观的地址面貌
geological feature discovered by Mariner 9
在高地的东部边缘是个
At the Eastern edge of the bulge is a colossal
红色行星外壳上的巨大裂口
tear in the crust of the red planet
它被阵为"水手谷" 水手谷
It's called "Valles Marineris", Mariner Valleys,
是水手9号给自己的荣誉
in honour of the Mariner 9 orbiter itself
你瞧这 它有美国这么宽
You look at this thing, it's like the width of the United States
它是劈开的峡谷
It's this cleaved valley
你知道美国的大峡谷吗？
You know the Grand Canyon in the United States?
把它拿起来 放大胆 把它弄得象美国一样大小
Pump it up, put it on steroids, make it the size of the United States itself
你就得到了水手谷
and you got Mariner Valleys
导致这巨大的裂口在火星表面的地质构造
The geological mechanism that causes this immense rupture in the martian surface
至今仍然是个谜 科学家只能进行猜测
is yet a mistery Scientists can only speculate
我喜欢的一个构造
One mechanism which I like
在那个叫做塔尔西斯高地不远
is that there's a place called Tharsis bulge not far away
它是许多熔岩和其他东西堆积起来的
And it's so much lava and other things have accumulated,
充满了熔岩并能把一个巨大的环放在火星表面
that it's filled and could put a giant torque on the surface of Mars
象拉链那样扯开
And pulled this apart like a zip
好啦 谁知道那是真实的…
Well, who knows if that's true...
需要一个不同于我们了解的任何事情的构造
but one needs a mechanism dfferent from many things we know
去解释它的存在
to explain the existence of that
由于水手9号的极其成功
With the stunning success of Mariner 9
NASA下一个采取的步骤
the next logical step for NASA
是用太空船登陆火星表面
was to land a spacecraft on the actual surface of Mars
科学家渴望测试岩石和土壤样本 寻找生命的踪迹
Scientists were eager to test rock and soil samples for sign of life
1976年 海盗号到达火星 完成这个使命
In 1976 the Viking mission reached the planet to do just that
它有卫星和登陆平台组成
It had both an orbiter and a landing component
装备有机器人测试仪器
equipped with robotic test instruments
我们已经降落在地面上了 铲起土壤和…
And we get right down on the surface and scoop up some soil and...
没有发现什么
we don't find a thing
火星看上去象是个寒冷 干燥 荒漠之地
Mars looks like a cold, dry, dead place
不过虽然海盗登陆车在地下劳而无功 没造成轰动效应
But while the Viking lander toiled the way underground failing to make headlines,
但是在火星高处
high above the martian surface
海盗登陆车还是设法捕捉到了迷人的图象
the Viking orbiter managed to capture a mystifying image
在飞越火星名叫基多尼亚的区域时
While flying over a region of Mars called Cydonia,
卫星拍摄到了一幅在交叉照亮下的地表造型
the orbiter snapped an image of a land formation under cross lighting
初一看造型象张人脸
Startingly the formation resembled a human face
作为一个笑话 NASA的科学家把图片作为新闻发表
As a joke NASA scientists showed the photos to the press
说是他们在火星上发现的面孔
remarking about the face they'd found on Mars
在更加均匀的照明下 当然
Under more even lighting conditions, of course
那个火星地貌怎么看都不象一张脸
the martian terrain feature doesn't look like a face at all
只是一群山丘
Just a jumble of hills
但在火星上的脸的故事到处流传时
But in certain circles the story of the face on Mars
NASA坚持掩盖了几年
and its NASA cover up persisted for several years
其他方面的火星爱好者跟随海盗号
True Mars enthusiasts on the other hand face a more sober reality
面临着一个更加清醒的现实
following the Viking mission
随着海盗号探险传来的没有生物现象的确切证据
With no definitive evidence of biology resulting from the Viking experiments,
对红色星球的兴趣平静了数年
interest in returning to the red planed quieted for several years
接着 在1984年
Then, in 1984,
一位在南极远征的年轻科学家
a young scientist on an expedition in Antarctica,
得到了注入新的活力的发现
made a discovery that ultimately infused new energy
唤起了揭示火星上生命的希望
and hope into the quest to uncover life on Mars
在1984年12月
In December 1984
NASA地质学家在南极收集陨石时
NASA geologist, on a meteorite gathering expedition in Antarctica,
找到了一个古老的样本
found an odd specimen
陨石有着不一样的颜色
A meteorite with an unusual colour
有点绿色
A sort of green hue
大部分是灰色或褐色
Most are grey or brown
回到NASA在休斯敦的约翰逊太空中心
Back at NASA's Johnsons space center in Houston,
那里储存着大量的石头
where such rocks are stored,
它的编号是ALH84001
it was labeled ALH84001
不管它古老的颜色
Despite its odd colour,
科学家设想它是小行星的碎片
the scientists assumed that it was a piece of an asteroid
所以石头被归类在陨石组
So the rock was pigeonholed into a group of meteorites,
被放置了6或者8年
and it stayed there for six or eight years
错误的分类
Misclassified
接着在90年代初期
Then, in the early 1990s,
一个分析员 研究小行星
an analyst, researching asteroids,
拿起这片ALH84001
placed a piece of ALH84001,
放到电子显微镜下
under an electron microscope
他很快意识到看到的不是块普通的陨石
He soon realized that he was not looking at a normal meteorite
看上去是块火星的碎片
He was looking at a piece of Mars
石头有着和1979年找到的火星陨石匹配的特征
The rock had characteristics that matched another Martian meteorite found in 1979
更多的科学家开始研究那个样本
More scientist began studying that sample,
他们感到惊讶
and they were astonished,
他们最后终于发现
when they eventually found,
有看上去象碳球的东西
what looked like carbon globules
碳 至少在地球上
Carbon, at least on Earth,
是构成生命的主要元素
is the primary building block of life
老资格的科学家大卫·麦凯
Senior scientist David McKay,
领军研究小组
headed up the research group
我的想象被碳酸盐印证了
My imagination was signated by the carbonates
我说"嘿 这些碳酸盐真是个奇怪的天体
And I said? "Hey, these carbonates are a really strange welkin
它们从哪来？让我们来瞧一下 "
How do they form? Let's look at those?"
小组全力投入在岩石样本旁
Closures groups near the rock sample,
但也带来了更纯正的发现
brought even more sterling discoveries
那些小珠里存在的化学成分
The kind of chemistry that went on in those globules,
是与地球上的生命相关联的
is associated with life on Earth
至少在电子显微镜扫描图像里
At least one, scanning electron microscope image,
显示出疑似存在有机物
revealed the structure that looked suspiciously organic
似乎象条虫子
Almost like a worm
会是原始的火星生物吗？
Could it be a trace of primitive Martian biology?
我认为那个虫子是…是…生物
I think that worm is... Is... biologic
不论细菌的化石有没有疑问
Whether is a complete fossil of bacterium is problematical,
它可能是细菌的一部分
it could be a part of that bacterium,
它可能是某种切片
it could be a section of one,
但是它在我眼里是个生物
but it's biologic in my view
"欢迎各位
"I'd like to welcome everybody here today
这是个难忘的日子
It's an unbelievable day
今天对我来说是非常非常激动"
It's very very exciting for me"
终于在1996年 在长达两年的研究后
Finally in 1996, after more than two years of study,
在他们在其中建立了4个独立证据的情况下
in which they have built four independent lines of evidence,
研究小组一切就绪
the team was ready
他们宣布了他们的假设
They announced their hypothesis
ALH84001包含了火星上可能存在生命的证据
ALH84001 contain possible evidence of passed life on Mars
"我们推定…
"We conclude that...
这是一个火星上的早期生命 "
This is evidence for early life on Mars"
NASA举行了一个大型的记者招待会
NASA held a major press conference,
然而不是每个人都相信
but not everyone was convinced
全球的实验室都要求将岩石的样本
Labs across the globe requested samples of the rock
让他们自己做分析
to conduct their own analysis
最后 在经过几个月的激烈辩论后
In the end, after months of at times acrimonius debate,
共识是…
the consensus was...
没有形成共识
That there was no consensus
发表的论文支持这个论点
Papers were published in support of the claim
但是更多的则持反对意见
but many more were published ebunking the idea
"如果我们来看第一张幻灯片
"If I could have the first slide please?
你看到的这个特写
The features that you see,
可能是一些物体 例如 可能会…"
may be any number of things, for example, they could..."
许多研究员确信那是岩石的成分
Many researchers are conviced that the formations in the rock,
那个似乎是火星生命的痕迹
that appeared to be signs of Martian life,
实际上是由矿物活性造成的
were actually caused by mineral activity
多数人会说
The majority of people would say that
来自这个火星早期的陨石
there's no really biogenic activity
其实没有生物活动
from this meteorite from Mars
开头那些推论是错误的
Those initial hypothesis was incorrect
我可以说在这一点上…
I would say at this point that...
作出的推论太天真了
That's too simple hypothesis to take
我不认为得到一个满意的结果
I don't think the work is being completed to
研究就完成了
a satisfactory end point
也就是说不论怎样
To say either way
关于陨石的研究还在继续
Work on the meteorite is continuing
但即使研究员从未证实岩石存在火星生命的痕迹
But even if researchers never confirmed that the rock contains signs of Martian life,
ALH84001有趣事件已经完全给寻找红色星球生命
the ALH84001 episode has already completely reinvigorated interest
注入了新的重要性
in the quest for life on the red planet
具有讽刺意义的是 寻找火星生命的新动力
Ironically, the new push to find life on Mars,
往往引导科学家再次前往南极大陆
has often led scientists yet again to the continent of Antarctica
地球上这个地方的环境与火星上的环境相似
Conditions, in this part of the world, are analogues in many ways to conditions on Mars
寻找生命形态在这个极端环境下
Seeking out life forms that managed to thrive
形成繁衍 可能揭示
an extreme circumstances here, might shed light
原始生命曾经能否在红色星球上生存
on how and where primitive life could have once taken hold on the red planet
环境天体生物学家Dale Andersen关注的是
What environment astrobiologist, Dale Andersen, focuses on,
那个全年覆盖厚厚的冰的湖底
is that the bottom of lakes, covered year-around, with thick layers of ice
大多数人说是由于冰盖的作用吗？
Most people said that because of the ticks ice covers?
"你除了岩石以外 什么都不会发现 "
"You would find nothing but rocks?"
湖底没东西 希望非常渺茫
There'll be very little to nothing on the bottom
冰层封锁许多这样的湖泊
The ice layer sealing off many of these lakes,
冰层厚达15英尺
is up to 15 feet thick
不过 要么炸开它 要么钻通它
But rather than trying to blast or drill through it,
干扰下面的生态系统
and disturbing the ecosystem below,
Andersen及其伙伴找到了大大减少破坏的办法
Andersen and team have found a much less damaging approach
他们用一大盘铜线圈制作一个通道
They let a massive coil of copper tubing make an opening
然后就用热的液体通过
Then you just pass a hot liquid through it,
将它投在冰上 使冰融化降下去
throw it down on the ice and it'll melt its way down
用了24小时化开了冰
It takes about 24 hours to melt through the ice
然后用这个漂亮的窟窿进行潜水
and then makes this very nice clean hole to dive through
潜水员身穿潜水服潜到水里
Divers enter the water wearing full-body drysuits
他们发现几乎每一个南极湖泊的湖底
And what they find at the bottom of nearly every Antarctical lake pad,
都是生命坚韧不拔的最好证据
is a testament to the stubborn ternacity of life
有机微生物丛
Mats of microbial organisms
在没有任何阳光的极度寒冷的环境下繁衍
are thriving in frigid enviroments that receive virtually no sunlight
大多数人会认为 在不足地表光线1%的地方
Most people thought that, if you have less than about 1% of the surface light,
在那个湖底 不可能进行光合作用
you won't have any photosynthesis taking place, down on the bottom
没有足够的光 不会变老
They won't be old to use enough light to live
结果是光照水平下降到10% 到1% 它们还能进行光合作用
It's turned out that they can photosynthesis with light levels down to 1/10 to 1%
对安徒生和他的团队来说
For Andersen and his team
原始的生物丛真是通往过去的一个窗口
the pristine mats are truly a window to the past
这里没有空调有机体 没有鱼类 没有昆虫
There no air organism, no fish, no insects,
没有爬行动物 这些微生物种落
no animals creeping through it, so these microbial communities
不论动 植物再无干扰下 通过其自身依然有生长的机会
have the opportunity to grow by themselves without interference, no matter animal or plants
并让他们有机会以非常特殊的方式生长
And that gives them the opportunity to grow in very special ways
这可能微生物生命类似的形态
Is it possible that a similar form of microbial life
还会生存在火星恶劣的表面之下？
could still reside somewhere beneath the frozen surface of Mars?
特别是在氢含量高的极地？
Especially at the hydrogen-rich poles?
Andersen和科学家们希望是这样 相信这是值得研究的
Andersen and scientists like it Believe it is worth investigating
倒计时 十 九 八 七 六
T-Minus 10... 9... 8... 7... 6...
五… 四… 三… 二…
5... 4... 3... 2...
Delta2号带着火星探险机器人升空了
And lifted off the Delta-2 rocket with the Mars exploration robot
在2003年夏季
In the Summer of 2003,
NASA的喷气推进实验室派出了两台探测飞船
NASA's jet propulsion laboratory, delivered two exploration spacecrafts,
到火星的表面去
to the surface of Mars
到红色星球去进行每两年一次的会面
Missions to the red planet are only feasible once every two years,
这是一次短暂的时间窗口
during a specific short window of time
发射必须准时
The launch must be timed,
使飞船和火星在同一时间到达火星轨道的
so that the spacecraft and Mars arrive at a specific point in the planet's orbit
一个特定的点
at the same time
横跨3400万英里距离需要7个月
The journey across the 34 million mile distance can take up to seven months
轨道必须精确
And the trajectory must be perfect
需要精确到从地球到火星
The accuracy required to go from Earth to Mars
并击中火星上你想要的点
and to hit the spot you want to be at on Mars
这相当于从洛杉矶投蓝进纽约的蓝筐
is equivalent to shoot in a basketball from Los Angeles to New York
并且通过时要不碰蓝框 不过没什么
And have it go trough without hitting the rib Nothing but that
所有的系统已经输入了登陆的程序
All systems are go for entering the step landing
我们现在6分钟后开始
We are currently 6 minutes from landing
在火星向阳面的古瑟夫坑登陆
at the Gusev crater of solar hemisphere of Mars
锁定每小时1 356英里
Point lock at 1 356 miles per hour
预计5秒钟后打开降落伞
Expecting parachute deploy in 5 seconds
探测到降落伞
Parachute detected
已经到达
Expecting reach
太空船实际上成了漫游者
The spacecrafts were actually rovers
遥控车能够在火星表面行走
Robotic vehicles capable of travelling across the martian surface
并捅开包围物体
and poking around
漫游者是机器地质学家
The rovers are robot geologist
它们干的活是在火星上当我们的眼睛 我们的脚和手
Their job is to be our eyes, our feet, our hands on the Martian surface
我们通过它们探索火星
We experience Mars through them
它们能伸出去 能接触岩石
They can reach out They can touch rocks
这是叫做Rat的装置
There's this device called the Rat
R A T (岩石磨具)是一个钻石磨头的工具
R A T the Rock Abrasion Tool wich is a diamond-tip grinding tool that we can use
我们能够用来打孔进入岩石内部
to grind into the interior of a rock,
所以我们实际上把它作为进入岩石的窗口
and so we can actually get a window inside the rock
它们有个装在机械臂末端的传感器 象个显微镜
They have sensors on the end of that arm like there's a microscope,
来告诉我们它们看到的一切
for telling us in detail what they look like
所以我们有整套的工具 类似地质学家想要的
So we've got a whole bunch of tools, similar to what the geologists would want,
如同他们亲临现场
if they were actually phisically there on the scene
漫游者被命名为精灵号和机会号
The rovers were named Spirit and Opportunity
直到今天它们仍然在火星上探索
and they are still exploring regions of Mars today,
在火星表面相互相距数百英里
at locations on the planet hundreds of miles from eachother
精灵号降落在古瑟夫坑
Spirit landed in an area dubbed Gusev crater
机会号相信是在干燥的湖床上
The crater is believed to be a dried up lake bed
所以如果水里曾经有过生物
So if the water it once held contains biology,
精灵号会发现它的痕迹
Spirit might uncover signs of it
机会号降落在叫做梅里迪亚尼平原的区域
Opportunity touched down in a region called Meridiani Planum
这个区域很奇特 因为它含有一层赤铁矿
The area is a triggy, because it contains an ancient layer of hematite
一层氧化铁 在地球上通常会含有水份
an iron oxyd that on Earth usually formes in a spot that held liquid water
到目前为止 两个漫游者都没有发现生命的痕迹
So far neither rovers has found signs of life
但是精灵号和机会号都发现了有价值的证据
But both Spirit and Opportunity have uncovered helpful proof
即在火星表面曾经存在过大量的水
that liquid water was once plentiful on the surface of the Red Planet
我们看到了水地表下被水浸泡过的岩石
We've seen places where water soaked the rocks beneath the surface,
看到了水曾在其表面流淌过的地方 在整个火星表面
we've seen places where water came to surface and flowed, over the martian
制造了小小的波纹 仍然保存在岩石里
surface creating little ripples that are still preserved in the rocks
长达数十亿年
billions of years later
然而两个漫游者都没有靠近火星极地的冻土带
But neither rovers is close enough to the tundra-like martian Poles
去揭示实际冻结的水
to uncover actual frozen H2O
那是新的火星任务的第一目标 2007年夏季启程
That is the primary goal of a new mission to Mars, launched in the summer of 2007
这一使命称为凤凰 计划到固定的登陆点
This mission is dubbed Phoenix, and its plan is to place a stationary lander
在火星的北极
in the reaching of the martian North Pole
登陆车有个强劲的机械臂 装有一个铲子
The lander has a sturdy robotic arm, equipped with a scoop
凤凰将挖掘极地的土壤
Phoenix will excavate the polar soil
亚利桑那大学的彼得·史密斯博士领导这个项目
Doctor Peter Smith of the University of Arizona heads up the project
我们完整的科学计划是关于
Our entire scientific mission is about
研究土壤的性质 以及冰对它的作用
understanding the properties of the soil, and its inner action with the ice,
还有冰的性质和冰与空气的相互作用
and the properties of the ice and the ice inner action with the atmosphere
我们只有一个办法研究它 那就是靠我们的机械臂
We have only one way to study it, and that's by using our robotic arm
这就是我们的回报 将会在那挖条小沟
that's our back-o if you like That's gonna dig a little trench,
取得土壤和期望的湿土的样本 如果能找到的话
and provide samples of both soil and hopefully wet soil if we can find it,
还有冰 我们会分析那些样本
and ice and we will analyze those samples
用我们太空船上的装置来分析
with instruments on the deck of our spacecraft
登陆车会从火星表面发回信号
The lander will beam signals back from the martian surface
报告遥远的土壤和冰的分析结果
reporting the result of the remote soil and ice analysis
但在凤凰之前曾经在发射架上有过一次机会
But before Phoenix has even had a chance to make it off the launch pad,
新的难题在传奇的"火星上的水"被揭示出来
a new wrinkle in the saga of "Water on Mars" has revealed itself
一直在红色星球轨道上运行的太空飞船发回的图象
Images beamed back from a spacecraft currently orbiting the red planet,
显示了一个非常令人以外的事情
show evidence of a very unexpected event
看来在过去的一段时间里 流体曾经流淌过某些地方
It appears that a liquid flow of some sort has accurred within the last few years,
一个小沟槽在火星深峡谷的边缘
in a small gully at the edge of a deep martian ravine,
2001年 卫星发回了同一地方的照片
In 2001 the orbiter took photos of the exact same spot,
然而看起来没有任何感兴趣的地方
but nothing of interest showed up in those shots
新照片另一方面显示出在沟壑里有白色的残留物
The new photos on the other hand, showed a white residue in the gully
残留物看起来象在水流的左后方
A residue simingly left behind by a flow of liquid
水可能从地面上流出
possibly where water spurted from the ground
流过了几百码
and flowed for several hundred yards,
然后蒸发掉了
before transforming into vapor and vanishing
科学家至今没有明白怎么会有这么个水流
Scientists do not yet understand what might have caused such a flow,
许多人怀疑是来自内部的热
but many suspect that it's a result of some form of internal heat
火星必然还保持着热量
the planet must still contain
毫无疑问 这是个有火山活动的平原
Clearly, it's a plain that it's been vulcanically active,
我们所有的人都非常希望能在火星上一些地方找到含氢的物质
and all of us are very hopefully that some places on Mars we could find hydro-thermovets
我们不仅希望找到液态水 而且由于液态水暗示着
Not just beacause we want liquid water, but because liquid water implies that
将可以成为生命能发展和持续的环境
this might be an environment that life could developed and be maintained
这 当然全在于寻求生命
It is, of course, all about the search for life
所有说过和做过的
When all is said and done
惊人的科学之举
the engine driving all of the astonishing scientific afford
去探索红色星球是人类不懈的追求
to explore the red planet is the burning desire of human kind
在广袤的太空的其它地方或许存在着生命
to know if life exists elsewhere in the vast reaches of space
我想自从人类开化以来
I think humans have, since the dawn of consciousness,
就想知道我们为什么会在这里 就会想知道那里有什么
wondered why they're here and wondered what's up there
还想知道还会有其它的东西吗
and wondered if there's more
而 解答那些问题将会排进我们未来的日程
And... answering that question will sort of put us in some kind of prospective
某种程度上会知道我们地球在宇宙的什么地方
it'll tell us what our places in the universe, to some extent
在火星上寻找生命也会帮助我们了解
Finding life on Mars could also help us understand the origins of life
在我们自己的星球上生命的起源
on our own planet
而且实际上会是火星与地球之间
And that could actually be in the case of Mars and Earth
重要的联系
a significant connection
火星上本身能产生生命并能很好地适应火星环境
Mars developed life itself and maybe the conditions were right on Mars
但就不可能很好地适应地球环境
but they weren't right on Earth
然而火星传送生命给了地球
And yet Mars seeded our planet
也许通过陨石碰撞 火星的碎片抵达了地球
Perhaps through meteoritic collisions, pieces of Mars arrived on Earth
我们生命的细胞如今在这里繁衍 或许我们都曾经是火星人
We're cells of life and that actually grew here Maybe we could all be martians
或者也许相反 你知道 或许生命在我们这个行星起源
Or perhaps it was the reverse, you know, perhaps life originated on this planet,
然后移居火星
and moved to Mars
如果我们在火星上找到生命的证据 我们知道地球上有生命 当然
If we find evidence for life on Mars and we know there's life on Earth, of course
接下来在所有的行星上就可能会有生命
than there's probably life all over the place
宇宙可能充满着生命 但如果不是
The universe is probably teeming with life And if it didn't,
那就会使我们多了一点点特别的感觉
then it makes us feeling like we are a little bit more special
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing